L. Patrick Gray III Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
L. Patrick Gray III Papers 1931-2008
MSS86267
Gray, L. Patrick, III (Louis Patrick), 1916-2005
36,000 items
102 containers plus 2 classified and 3 oversize
42 linear feet
20,325 digital files (16.85 MB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, assistant attorney general for the United States Department of Justice Civil Division, and acting director of the United States Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI). Correspondence, memoranda, notes, writings, speeches, testimony, legal records, military records, photographs, printed matter, and other papers relating chiefly to Gray's time as acting director of the FBI during the Richard M. Nixon presidential administration and the impact of this period on his life in the following years. Topics include the investigation of the Watergate Affair, other FBI actions in 1972 and 1973, and changes in that institution following the death of J. Edgar Hoover.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bell, Griffin B., 1918-2009--Trials, litigation, etc.; Felt, W. Mark, 1913-2008.; Gray family.; Gray, Ed. In Nixon's web: a year in the crosshairs of Watergate. 2008.; Gray, L. Patrick, III (Louis Patrick), 1916-2005.; Gray, L. Patrick, III (Louis Patrick), 1916-2005. In Nixon's web: a year in the crosshairs of Watergate. 2008.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Miller, Edward S. (Edward Samuel), 1923-2013.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Sachs, Stephen H.; Wallace, George C. (George Corley), 1919-1998--Assassination attempts.
Organizations
American Indian Movement.; Democratic National Committee (U.S.); United States. Congress. Senate. Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities.; United States. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare.; United States. Department of Justice. Civil Division.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation.; United States. Navy.; United States. Watergate Special Prosecution Force.; Weather Underground Organization.; Weatherman (Organization)
Subjects
Governmental investigations--United States.; Hijacking of aircraft.; Political corruption--United States.; Practice of law--United States.; Terrorism.; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974.
Places
United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; United States--Politics and government--1974-1977.; Wounded Knee (S.D.)--History--Indian occupation, 1973.
Occupations
Lawyers.; Public officials.
Provenance
The papers of L. Patrick Gray III were purchased from his family by the Library of Congress in 2018.
Transfers
Audiotapes have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of the L. Patrick Gray III Papers.
Access and Restrictions
Restictions apply governing the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for information concerning these restrictions. In addition, many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Digital files were created in a Windows operating system, version unknown. The content is primarily image files in .jpg and .tiff formats and text files in .doc, .txt, and .pdf formats. Audio files in .wav and .wma formats and moving image files in .VOB, .mp3, and .mp4 formats are also included.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified materials.
Digital Format
Digital files were received as part of the papers of L. Patrick Gray. A digital ID number was assigned to each digital storage media. Researchers should use the digital ID number to request access copies of the files. Access to digital content is available onsite only in the Manuscript Reading Room and requires advanced notice. Researchers should consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for more information.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1916, July 18 Born, St. Louis, Mo.
1932 1936 Attended Rice Institute, Houston, Tex.
1936 1940 Attended United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1940 1942 Served aboard Idaho (battleship)
1942 1944 Served aboard Steelhead (submarine)
1944 1945 Executive officer and navigator, Bumper (submarine)
1945 1946 Executive officer and navigator, Caiman (submarine)
1946 Married Beatrice Kirk De Garmo
1949 J.D., George Washington University, Washington, D.C.
1949 1950 Staff, Commander Submarine Force, United States Pacific Fleet, Pearl Harbor, Hawaii
1950 1952 Commanding officer, Tiru (submarine)
1953 1955 Executive officer, planning officer, and budget and fiscal officer, United States Naval School of Naval Justice, Newport, R.I.
1955 1956 Executive officer, Fulton (submarine tender)
1956 1957 Commander, Submarine Division 101
1958 1960 Military assistant to chairman of Joint Chiefs of Staff and special assistant to the secretary of defense in area of legal, legislative, and politico-military affairs, Department of Defense, Washington, D.C.
1960 Retired as captain, United States Navy
1960 1961 Special assistant to Vice President Richard M. Nixon Participated in Nixon’s presidential campaign
1961 1969 Practiced law, Suisman, Shapiro, Wool, Brennan, and Gray, New London, Conn.; partner, 1967
1969 1970 Executive assistant to secretary, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, Washington, D.C.
1970 1972 Assistant attorney general, Civil Division, Department of Justice, Washington, D.C.
1972 Nominated to be deputy attorney general, Department of Justice Appointed acting director, Federal Bureau of Investigation, Washington, D.C.
1973 Nominated to be director, Federal Bureau of Investigation in Feb.; nomination withdrawn in April Resigned from Federal Bureau of Investigation in April Testified before House Committee on Armed Services Special Subcommittee on Intelligence, Senate Committee on Appropriations subcommittee, and Senate Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities regarding Watergate Affair
1973 1974 Testified before Watergate grand jury, United States District Court for the District of Columbia
1973 1975 Investigated by Watergate Special Prosecution Force
circa 1974 circa 1990 Partner, Suisman, Shapiro, Wool, Brennan, and Gray, New London and Groton, Conn.
1978 Indicted, with W. Mark Felt and Edward S. Miller, for authorizing surreptitious entry into the homes of family and friends of Weather Underground (Weatherman) fugitives
1980 Charges against Gray dropped
2005, July 6 Died, Atlantic Beach, Fla.
2008 Publication of In Nixon’s Web: A Year in the Crosshairs of Watergate with Ed Gray. New York: Henry Holt & Co.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Louis Patrick Gray III (1916-2005) span the years 1931-2008. The collection focuses on Gray's time as acting director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) during the administration of President Richard M. Nixon and the impact of this period on his life in the following years. The papers are organized into eight series: General Correspondence, Federal Bureau of Investigation, Legal File, Speeches and Writings, Alphabetical File, Closed, Classified, and Oversize.
While the L. Patrick Gray III Papers contain material relating to his military career in the United States Navy, his work as a lawyer in private practice, and his positions in the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare and the Department of Justice in the early years of the presidency of Richard M. Nixon, the major focus of the papers is Gray’s experience as the acting head of the FBI, following the death of J. Edgar Hoover, from May 1972 to April 1973. The Watergate Affair is a key topic; the papers chronicle the FBI investigation into the break-in at the Democratic National Committee headquarters, Gray’s actions at the time, and his recounting and explanation of these events during testimony at congressional hearings and before grand juries, while under investigation by the Watergate Special Prosecution Force, and in preparation for writing a book. The changes and tensions in the FBI following the death of J. Edgar Hoover are another topic covered in the material. The collection also chronicles Gray’s indictment, along with W. Mark Felt (associate director of the FBI), and Edward S. Miller (head of the FBI's Domestic Intelligence Division), for allegedly authorizing break-ins aimed at locating Weather Underground (Weatherman) fugitives while he was acting director of the FBI. Originals and copies of memoranda, reports, notes, testimony, and correspondence relating to Gray’s actions and those of others in the FBI in response to events in 1972 and 1973 appear in numerous series throughout the collection because Gray used documents from his personal FBI files as background and exhibits in hearings and legal proceedings and as resource material for a prospective memoir. Some documents contain dated comments written by Gray when he reviewed them in later years. Additional material was compiled by his son, Ed Gray, in the preparation of Gray’s posthumous memoir. W. Mark Felt figures prominently in the collection.
A small General Correspondence series contains letters received by Gray and copies of his responses. They are primarily of a personal nature and most date from the 1970s and 1980s. Correspondents include FBI agents and officials, figures from the Nixon administration, and friends. A number are letters of support and congratulations when the charges against Gray were dropped in 1980. A file of correspondence with W. Mark Felt also contains notes on telephone conversations and copies of letters Gray sent to his lawyer in response to one of Felt’s letters.
The Federal Bureau of Investigation series comprises files generated during Gray’s year as acting director. Position papers on issues, practices, and proposed changes at the FBI, memoranda to special agents in charge, notes Gray took at meetings, and notes he added to routing slips illuminate the actions of the FBI under his leadership. Information relating to the Watergate Affair is scattered throughout the collection, but among the material found in this series is the Watergate detailed memoranda file Gray used at his confirmation hearings, general investigation division summaries of the break-in investigation, a compilation of questions and answers, and digital files containing scans of the FBI’s Watergate file obtained through a Freedom of Information Act request. Other files relate to the hijacking of aircraft, the George C. Wallace assassination attempt, the American Indian Movement occupation at Wounded Knee, South Dakota, and the Weatherman. Also included are a compilation of press clippings about Gray and the FBI during that period, congratulatory correspondence, and letters sent to Gray after the withdrawal of his nomination. Some documents that had once been part of Gray’s FBI files are now part of other series. The Legal File series contains documents Gray used as exhibits when he testified before the Watergate hearings of the Senate Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities, as documentation submitted in response to the investigation by the Watergate Special Prosecution Force, and as part of his defense in the United States v. Gray. Although United States v. Gray centered on actions taken with regard to the Weatherman, documents pulled together as general exhibits also pertain to the FBI response to other events including the Watergate burglary investigation and the American Indian Movement occupation at Wounded Knee, South Dakota. Speeches delivered by Gray as acting FBI director and documents he gathered as resource material for his memoir are located in the Speeches and Writings series.
The Legal File series documents Gray’s involvement in congressional hearings, grand juries, investigations, and federal and civil legal cases in the years after his resignation from the FBI that stemmed from his tenure as acting director. Gray's relationship with his lawyers is evident throughout the series. Notes Gray wrote for his lawyers describe his memories and thoughts about the issues under consideration and explain the documents he reviewed to prepare for testimony or plan his legal defense. His detailed notes of telephone conversations and correspondence with his attorneys recount his feelings about the legal investigations and prosecution as well as statements about him in the press. Gray’s files are supplemented by those kept by his lawyer, Stephen H. Sachs. The bulk of the files relate to the Watergate Affair and United States v. Gray. FBI memoranda, notes, and reports relating to the investigation into the break-in at the Democratic National Committee headquarters, press reporting on the investigation, and leaks to the press are included in a set of numbered exhibits pertaining to Gray’s Senate Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities. Additional documents relating to Gray’s actions were submitted in response to requests by the Watergate Special Prosecution Force and are filed with material on that investigation. Among the files compiled during the course of United States v. Gray are discovery documents and exhibits pertaining to the FBI procedures and the response to terrorism and events of the period. Gray v. Bell, the lawsuit Gray filed against Attorney General Griffin Bell and others after the charges against him were dropped, is among the material pertaining to civil litigation in which he was involved. Transcripts and notes about grand jury testimony are filed in the Closed series.
The Speeches and Writings series features writings, recordings, and resource material that Gray created and compiled for a book project he began in the 1970s and early 1980s but discontinued until the end of his life when his son, Ed Gray, resumed work on the memoir and published In Nixon’s Web: A Year in the Crosshairs of Watergate three years after his father's death. Among the book project material are handwritten narratives, sample chapter drafts, recordings, and edited transcripts of tape recordings Gray made in 1978-1979. A numerical file contains resource material that Gray compiled; original folders with his original labels have been retained. Among the material relating to In Nixon’s Web are digital files documenting Ed Gray’s research and resource material, including scans of documents from Bob Woodward and Carl Bernstein’s papers at the Harry Ransom Center at the University of Texas at Austin, and transcripts and recordings of conversations from Nixon’s White House tapes. Typescripts of speeches and remarks delivered by Gray while at the Department of Justice and the FBI are also part of this series.
The Alphabetical File series contains material pertaining to other phases of Gray’s life, including his tenures as executive assistant to secretary of the Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Robert Finch, and assistant attorney general for the Department of Justice's Civil Division. Appointment books, photographs, and a scrapbook supplement those files. A grouping of military papers document Gray’s twenty-year career in the United States Navy and includes copies of Gray’s letters to friends and relations that provide details about his family life. Files from the Pat Gray Legal Defense Fund document the effort by United States Naval Academy classmates and other supporters to ease the financial burden of years of legal defense. A press problems file reveals Gray's reaction to statements about him in the press, and his annotations in books written by others about the FBI offer Gray's thoughts on their accounts of him and his tenure there. Material from the last year of Gray's life focuses on his private and public response to W. Mark Felt's announcement in 2005 that he was "Deep Throat," the informant who assisted Bob Woodward and Carl Bernstein with their reporting on the Watergate Affair.
The remaining series comprises a Closed segment of material relating to grand jury testimony, Classified documents, and Oversize items.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in eight series:
General Correspondence, 1945-2006
Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1931-1979
Legal File, 1955-1981
Speeches and Writings, 1941-2008
Alphabetical File, 1936-2008
Closed, 1973-1977
Classified, 1946-1981
Oversize, 1949-1973
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1945-2006 (Box 1-3)
  The General Correspondence series contains letters received by Gray and copies of his responses, primarily of a personal nature, and mostly dating from the 1970s and 1980s. A few notes about telephone conversations and other related material are filed with the correspondence.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - A-E miscellaneous, 1961-1964, 1971-1990, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Felt, W. Mark and Audrey, 1973-1981 (Box 1)
  - F miscellaneous, 1970-1974, 1980-1985, 1998, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Gates, Thomas S., 1961, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Gray family, 1945, 1978-1980, 1994-1995, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  - G miscellaneous, 1967-1985, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Held, Richard G., 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - H-J miscellaneous, 1971-1985, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Kalmbach, Herbert W., 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Kelley, Clarence M., 1974-1982 (Box 2)
  - Kleindienst, Richard G., 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - K-L miscellaneous, 1967, 1973-1986, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Mullen, Francis M., 1981-1983 (Box 2)
  - M miscellaneous, 1971-1985, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1961, 1967-1973 (Box 2)
  - N-R miscellaneous, 1967, 1972-1991, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Sachs, Stephen H., 1978-1983 (Box 3)
  - S-V miscellaneous, 1966-1985, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Webster, William H., 1978-1984 (Box 3)
  - Weicker, Lowell P., Jr., 1973-1981, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Woods, Rose Mary, 1968-1973, 1980 (Box 3)
  - W-Z miscellaneous, 1960, 1971-1985, 1994-1995, 2002, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Unidentified, 1972-1974, 1980-1985 (Box 3)
- Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1931-1979 (Box 3-21)
  The Federal Bureau of Investigation series comprises files generated during Gray’s year as acting director from May 1972 to April 1973. Types of material include correspondence, memoranda, reports, daily logs, notes, press clippings, and digital files.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic, name, or type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Acting director (Box 3)
    - Congratulatory letters, 1972 (Box 3)
      - A-C, (5 folders) (Box 3)
      - D-K, (8 folders) (Box 4)
      - L-R, (7 folders) (Box 5)
      - S, (1 folder) (Box 5)
      - S, (2 folders) (Box 6)
      - T-Z, (5 folders) (Box 6)
    - Miscellany, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Administrative changes, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Al Fatah (organization), 1972-1979 See also Classified (Box 6)
  - Black, Creed C., 1970-1973 (Box 6)
  - Chapin, B. Russell, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
  - Committee for the Re-election of the President, undated (Box 7)
  - Confirmation hearings (Box 7)
    - Anderson, Jack, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - Congressional correspondence, 1973 (Box 7)
    - Contacts with John W. Dean and John Ehrlichman, 1972-1973, 1979, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Mardian, Robert C., 1973 (Box 7)
    - Memoranda, 1973 (Box 7)
    - Miscellany, 1973 (Box 7)
    - Statements (Box 7)
      - 1973, Feb. 28, (3 folders) (Box 7)
      - 1973, Mar. (Box 8)
    - Watergate detailed memoranda, 1972-1973, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Corruption in the FBI, draft statement, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Daily logs (Box 8)
    - 1972-1973, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - DeLoach, Cartha D., 1973 (Box 8)
  - Democratic National Committee headquarters burglary investigation (Box 8)
    - General Investigation Division summaries, 1972-1973, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Memoranda, 1973 (Box 9)
    - Miscellany, 1972-1973, 1979 For additional material see Containers 38-39, Exhibits (Box 9)
    - Watergate file, Freedom of Information Act request, 1972-1974, mss86267_175_003; mss86267_175_004; mss86267_175_005
    - Watergate questions and answers, 1972-1973, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Domestic intelligence briefings, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Electronic surveillance, 1973 For additional see Containers 52-53, Wiretap investigation (Box 9)
  - Events and issues, White House memo request, 1972 (Box 9)
  - F.B.I. jurisdiction, 1972 (Box 10)
  - FBI Law Enforcement Bulletin, 1972 (Box 10)
  - Finch, Robert H., 1971-1972 (Box 10)
  - Haddad, William F., 1972-1973 (Box 10)
  - Hijacking of aircraft (Box 10)
    - General, 1970-1973 (Box 10)
    - Southern Airways, 1972 (Box 10)
  - International Telephone and Telegraph Corp. (ITT), 1971-1973 (Box 10)
  - Johnson, Marlin W., 1973 (Box 10)
  - Long-range objectives, 1972-circa 1973, 1978 (Box 10)
  - Mason, Edmund D., 1972-1973 (Box 10)
  - Meeting with police chiefs, 1972 (Box 10)
  - Message to assistant directors and special agents in charge regarding Watergate investigation files, 1973 (Box 10)
  - Miscellany, 1931-1932, 1972-1973, (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - National Symposium on Terrorism, F.B.I. Academy, Quantico, Va., Jan. 16, 1973, 1972-1973, 1978 (Box 11)
  - Nomination (Box 11)
    - Congratulatory letters, 1973 (Box 11)
      - A-J, (8 folders) (Box 11)
      - K-T, (10 folders) (Box 12)
      - U-Z See also Oversize, (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - Letters of support to members of Congress, 1973, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Letters regarding withdrawal, 1973 (Box 13)
      - A-G, (6 folders) (Box 13)
      - H-Z, (12 folders) (Box 14)
    - Press release, 1972 (Box 15)
    - Request for withdrawal for nomination, 1973 (Box 15)
  - Notes, miscellaneous, 1972-1973 (Box 15)
  - Notes attached to routing slips, 1972-1973, (4 folders) (Box 15)
  - Ostrow, Ronald J., 1972 (Box 16)
  - Position papers, 1972, (4 folders) (Box 16)
  - Press (Box 16)
    - Clippings (Box 16)
      - 1972 (Box 16)
        - Articles (Box 16)
          - May-Aug., (2 folders) (Box 16)
          - May-Aug., (1 folder) (Box 17)
          - Sept.-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 17)
        - Cartoons (Box 17)
        - Editorials, (2 folders) (Box 17)
      - 1973, Mar., (6 folders) (Box 18)
    - Miscellany, 1972-1973 (Box 18)
    - Time magazine, 1972-1973 (Box 18)
  - Reorganization, 1972-1973 (Box 19)
  - Resignation, 1973 (Box 19)
  - Riley, Thomas F., 1973 (Box 19)
  - Scoville, Harmon G., 1972 (Box 19)
  - Security, Gray family, 1971-1973 (Box 19)
  - Smith, E. Dell, 1972-1973 (Box 19)
  - Smith, Robert, 1972 (Box 19)
  - Special agents in charge (Box 19)
    - Conferences, 1972, 1976 (Box 19)
    - Memoranda, 1972-1973, (3 folders) (Box 19)
  - Speeches, 1972-1973 (Box 19)
  - Sullivan, William C., 1972-1973 (Box 19)
  - Training (Box 20)
    - 1972-1973, (3 folders) (Box 20)
  - Travel, 1972-1973, (5 folders) (Box 20)
  - Travel calendar, 1972-1973 (Box 21)
  - Wallace, George C., shooting, 1972 (Box 21)
  - Weatherman, 1972-1973 For additional material see Containers 24-36, United States v. Gray (Box 21)
  - Whitten, Les, arrest for possession of documents stolen from Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1973 (Box 21)
  - Wounded Knee, S.D., American Indian Movement Occupation, 1973 For additional material see Container 27, General exhibits (Box 21)
- Legal File, 1955-1981 (Box 21-53)
  The Legal File documents Gray’s involvement in congressional hearings, grand juries, investigations, and federal and civil legal cases in the years after his resignation from the FBI that stemmed from his tenure as acting director. Types of material include correspondence, memoranda, legal papers, notes, FBI documents used as exhibits, discovery documents, background material, statements, transcripts, and lawyer's files.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
  - Civil lawsuits (Box 21)